<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gender | Lee Edwards]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/categories/gender/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-05T22:49:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ledwards.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lee Edwards]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[leeredwards@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sexism for Dummies]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/2013/08/09/sexism-for-dummies/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-09T09:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/2013/08/09/sexism-for-dummies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I saw a <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mattgemmell/9465578396/">screenshot</a> of a hiring ad from a
<a href="http://www.bloopark.com">German web development agency</a> that is so blatantly sexist, it would be <a href="http://www.eeoc.gov/employees/charge.cfm">illegal in the United States</a>.</p>

<p>Occasionally when discussing charges of sexism in mixed company, I&rsquo;ll get someone who says they just don&rsquo;t get it. Like the <a href="http://www.hulu.com/watch/514294">Stephen Colbert segment on Color-blindness</a>, they claim they&rsquo;re just so equality-minded that they don&rsquo;t see subtle use of language as sexist. They reject the claim that choice of phrasing and subtle language cues can often betray a speaker or writer&rsquo;s prejudices and attitudes toward gender (I&rsquo;m thinking specifically of a conversation I once had with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/DBness">Vanessa Hurst</a> from <a href="http://www.girldevelopit.com/">GirlDevelopIt</a>).</p>

<p>Thankfully, this job posting makes no attempts to hide its prejudice. I think almost everyone can agree it&rsquo;s discriminatory and reveals quite a bit about the culture (or lack thereof) at the company in question. So I think it would make a great instructional tool to help the gender-blind understand some of the more subtle aspects of gender discrimination.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the job listing in question.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Lipstick</strong> Do all women like to wear lipstick? Don&rsquo;t some men like to wear lipstick? This graphic reiforces the idea of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_roles">gender roles</a>. It makes assumptions about the way women behave, and it implies that women in a workplace environment need to be more concerned about their appearance than men do (or else wouldn&rsquo;t the male listing feature a comb and razor?).</li>
<li></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
