<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: olin | Lee Edwards]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/categories/olin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-07T01:07:49-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ledwards.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lee Edwards]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[leeredwards@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Olin's Gay Shame]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/2013/07/11/olins-gay-shame/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T22:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ledwards.com/blog/2013/07/11/olins-gay-shame</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How would you feel, years later, about a college that issued a statement in support of Loving v. Virginia and then retracted it due to pressure from its alumns?</p>

<p>Today my alma mater &ldquo;officially&rdquo; <del>retracted</del> apologized for a Facebook post celebrating the repeal of DOMA, which allowed the many LGBT Olin College community members &ndash; faculty, staff, students, and alumns &ndash; who are married or will be married in the state of Massachusetts &ndash; to enjoy equal protection under federal law.</p>

<blockquote><p>As a matter of policy, Olin College does not endorse any political candidate or political cause, or any religious point of view.</p></blockquote>

<p>Where is the controversy? Marriage equality is now the law in your state and in your country. Does Olin College hold no official position on marriage between heterosexual couples?</p>

<p>Shame on you, whoever made that call. Ordering an employee to <del>remove</del> disown that post <em>was</em> a statement. It was a statement that you would rather disown the LGBT Olin community than risk offending the tender sensibilities of a few bigots. You&rsquo;ve helped create a piece of our collective memory around this historic decision, and it&rsquo;s not one that any of us can be proud of.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT 7/12/2013</strong>: It was called to my attention that Olin didn&rsquo;t actually delete the Facebook post, they only issued an apology for it. My mistake.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also worth mentioning that the original post had 120 likes and only 2 detractors. The Olin community is still a very open and accepting one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
